<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>mariadb on Chaos is order not yet deciphered</title><link>http://tomfern.com/tags/mariadb/</link><description>Recent content in mariadb on Chaos is order not yet deciphered</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 15:29:00 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://tomfern.com/tags/mariadb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Case study: MariaDB ColumnStore</title><link>http://tomfern.com/posts/case-study-mariadb-columnstore/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 15:29:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>http://tomfern.com/posts/case-study-mariadb-columnstore/</guid><description>A recent project I worked on provided an opportunity to work with MariaDB ColumnStore.
The Product 🔗The product is a business intelligence application. Its main view, a very comprehensive dashboard with an abundance of counters, showing all operational aspects: from server status, database backups, support tickets and SLA to datacenter atmospheric conditions.
In the middle of all this: several MariaDB databases fed through multiple ETL jobs.
As the application grew, the dashboard got increasingly more intricate.</description></item><item><title>Making the most out of Docker</title><link>http://tomfern.com/posts/making-the-most-out-of-docker/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 11:21:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>http://tomfern.com/posts/making-the-most-out-of-docker/</guid><description>Some options that might increase performance, some that don&amp;rsquo;t.
Network 🔗Containers get connected to a bridge network by default. A software bridge that allows communication between containers running on the same host &amp;amp; bridge. We can also create and use custom bridges, to create isolated groups of containers. To allow connections from outside, we must map the host&amp;rsquo;s ports to a container&amp;rsquo;s with -p (publish e.g. -p 3306:3306) This is easy and flexible, but it makes Docker start an additional process (docker-proxy), which can use a non-trivial amount of CPU.</description></item></channel></rss>