<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>docker on Chaos is order not yet deciphered</title><link>http://tomfern.com/tags/docker/</link><description>Recent content in docker on Chaos is order not yet deciphered</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 07:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://tomfern.com/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Always use ImagePullSecrets</title><link>http://tomfern.com/posts/always-use-imagepullsecrets/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 07:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>http://tomfern.com/posts/always-use-imagepullsecrets/</guid><description>Docker Hub introduced rate limits for image pulls earlier this month. Being the default registry for Docker images, this is one of the biggest in the ecosystem in the last few years, and it will affect not only Docker users but also Kubernetes setups.
The limits 🔗The new limits affect free users. No more unlimited free pulls, the party is over.
Anonymous free users: 100 container pulls every 6 hours.</description></item><item><title>Making the most out of Docker</title><link>http://tomfern.com/posts/making-the-most-out-of-docker/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 11:21:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>http://tomfern.com/posts/making-the-most-out-of-docker/</guid><description>Some options that might increase performance, some that don&amp;rsquo;t.
Network 🔗Containers get connected to a bridge network by default. A software bridge that allows communication between containers running on the same host &amp;amp; bridge. We can also create and use custom bridges, to create isolated groups of containers. To allow connections from outside, we must map the host&amp;rsquo;s ports to a container&amp;rsquo;s with -p (publish e.g. -p 3306:3306) This is easy and flexible, but it makes Docker start an additional process (docker-proxy), which can use a non-trivial amount of CPU.</description></item><item><title>A Container for My Databases</title><link>http://tomfern.com/posts/a-container-for-my-databases/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 17:59:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>http://tomfern.com/posts/a-container-for-my-databases/</guid><description>Who doesn&amp;rsquo;t like containers? Anyone doesn&amp;rsquo;t like to have most of the benefits of virtual machines with much, much less overhead?
They&amp;rsquo;ve been around since forever (anyone still remember chroot?) but only in recent years their popularity boomed, mainly due to cloud computing, I&amp;rsquo;m sure.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been running databases in docker for a while now. I was curious about other alternatives, so I did a bit of benchmarking.
Docker 🔗It&amp;rsquo;s not a coincidence that Docker appeared around the same time container technology began its popularity rise.</description></item></channel></rss>