<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>writing on Chaos is order not yet deciphered</title><link>/tags/writing/</link><description>Recent content in writing on Chaos is order not yet deciphered</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 07:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My Writing Process</title><link>/posts/my-writing-process/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 07:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>/posts/my-writing-process/</guid><description>My Technical Writing Process 🔗I tend to have a more suis generis process for writing technical documents. With this I mean I don’t have too much of a structure when it’s time to type. I usually do an outline first (but not always) and then write, edit, cut, redit, recut until I have something that’s, at the very least, decent.
But lately I’ve been paying more attention to how I write and I’ve noted that I’m kind of following a process after all.</description></item><item><title>Programming humans</title><link>/posts/programming-humans/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 07:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>/posts/programming-humans/</guid><description>While working on the slides for the talk I gave a few weeks ago, it occurred to me that writing and coding have more than a few things in common. I originally planned to speak a bit about that but had to take it out for lack of space. I&amp;rsquo;ll make a post instead, this one.
Thinks in common 🔗Language
Both writing and coding use a language. Writing happens in any of the hundreds of languages people speak all over the world.</description></item><item><title>What Got Me Writing</title><link>/posts/what-got-me-writing/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 07:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>/posts/what-got-me-writing/</guid><description>When I started freelancing, I never imagined I would end up writing for a living. Never in a hundred years. Yet, I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing it full-time for almost a year now.
I got interested in freelancing because I wanted to try something different. I needed a break from the office routine. The job was OK. I had excellent colleagues and was friends with everyone. And while it wasn&amp;rsquo;t making me rich by any means, I never lacked for anything.</description></item><item><title>10 Vim Plugins for Writers</title><link>/posts/10-vim-plugins-for-writers/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 14:04:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>/posts/10-vim-plugins-for-writers/</guid><description>I still remember the first time I came in contact with Vim; it was during my very first job. It was a part-time gig in a government office. A few months in, they decided to go open-source full in. Out the window went Windows and in came Linux. At the time, I was doing PHP development, and I was sorry to have to let go of my dear Dreamweaver.
I decided that if I had to work on Linux, I would go all the way, no compromises for me.</description></item></channel></rss>